<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>By the Queenes most excellent Maiestie. The Queenes most excellent Maiestie, being minded in this daungerous time to intertaine a certaine number of captaines and souldiers for the garding of her royall person  ...</title>
            <title>Proclamations. 1588-08-07</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1558-1603 : Elizabeth I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1588</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A21847</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 8173</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115395</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850614</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850614</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15826</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A21847)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15826)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 565:41)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>By the Queenes most excellent Maiestie. The Queenes most excellent Maiestie, being minded in this daungerous time to intertaine a certaine number of captaines and souldiers for the garding of her royall person  ...</title>
                  <title>Proclamations. 1588-08-07</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1558-1603 : Elizabeth I)</author>
                  <author>Elizabeth I, Queen of England, 1533-1603.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>2 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By the deputies of Christopher Barker, printer to the Queenes most excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1588. Cum priuilegio Regiæ Maiestatis]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Setting price ceilings for victuals, etc. for the army.--STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Operational rations (Military supplies) --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Army --  Commissariat --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Elizabeth, 1558-1603 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England --  Proclamations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:15826:1"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> By the Queenes moſt excellent Maieſtie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Queenes moſt excellent Maieſtie, being minded in this daungerous time to intertaine a certaine number of Captaines and ſouldiers for the garding of her royall perſon, and defence of this her Realme, to be vnder the gouernment and lieutenancie of the right honourable the Lorde Chamberlaine, hath thought it requiſite for the better and more eaſie reliefe of the ſayde armie by this her High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe Proclamation ſtraightly to charge and command, that all and euery per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and perſons of whatſoeuer eſtate or degree he or they be of, doe obſerue &amp; keepe ſuch rates and prices for all kinde of victuals, horſemeate, lodging, and other ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries, as from time to time ſhall be rated and priſed by the clarke of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket of her Highneſſe moſt honourable houſholde, or his lawfull Deputie or Deputies, and the Iurie before him or them by vertue of his office ſworne and charged. Which rates and priſes ſhall accordingly (during the time of ſuch attendance vpon her Maieſties perſon) be ſet vp and declared vpon her Highneſſe Court gates, and in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Towne, Village, Pariſh and Hamlet, where the ſaid Captaines and ſouldiers or any of them are to be pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, within the circuit of xx. miles euery way diſtant from her Highneſſe Court. And further her Maieſties plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and expreſſe commaundement is, That all Iuſtices of Peace, and all other her faithfull Officers reſiant within the ſaide circuit, ſhall diligently within their ſeuerall authorities (vpon iuſt complaint made for the breach or other abuſe of the ſame Aſſiſe) in the abſence of the ſaid Clarke of the Market, imploy themſelues to ſee due puniſhment inflicted vpon the offenders by impriſonment or otherwiſe, &amp;c. And alſo that no maner victualers or other perſon whatſoeuer, doe withholde, keepe backe, or hide any graine or other victuals, whereby the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets vſually heretofore ſerued within the ſaide precinct of xx. miles, might be vnfurniſhed thereof, vpon paine of their moſt grieuous impriſonment, and further fine to bee made to her Maieſties vſe for their contempt in this behalfe.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen at our Mannour of Saint Iames, <date>the ſeuenth day of Auguſt <hi>1588.</hi> in the xxx. yeere of our reigne.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <closer>God ſaue the Queene.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_prices">
            <head>A limitation of ſuch rates and prices of graine, victuals, horſemeat, lodgings, and <hi>other things, as by vertue of this Proclamation here aboue expreſſed, are to</hi> be ſold and vttered, aſwell within all maner of liberties, as without.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt a quarter beſt wheat cleane and ſweete in the Market. xx.<abbr>s.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>And a quarter ſecond wheate in the Market, xvi.<abbr>s.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Item a quarter third wheat or beſt rie in the Market. xii.<abbr>s.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>And a quarter ſecond rie in the Market. x.<abbr>s.</abbr> viii.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Item a quarter beſt barley in the Market. x.<abbr>s.</abbr> viii.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>And a quarter ſecond barley in the Market. ix.<abbr>s.</abbr> iiii.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Item a quarter beſt mault cleane and ſweete in the Market. xi.<abbr>s.</abbr> iiii.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>And a quarter ſecond mault, in the Market. x.<abbr>s.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Item a quarter beanes or peaſe in the Market. xii.<abbr>s.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Item a quarter beſt otes in the Market. vi.<abbr>s.</abbr> viii.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Item a buſhell of the ſame otes within every houſe xiii.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Item a buſhell beſt wheat meale in the Market. ii.<abbr>s.</abbr> viii.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>And a buſhell ſecond wheat meale in the Market. ii.<abbr>s.</abbr> vi.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Item a buſhell beſt meſtling meale in the Market. xxi.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>And a buſhell ſecond meſtling meale in the Market. xviii.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:15826:2"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:15826:3"/>
               <item>Item a buſhell beſt great otemeale in the Market. ii.<abbr>s.</abbr> iiii.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>And a buſhell ſmall otemeale in the Market. xvi.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Item a kilderkin of the beſt Ale or Beere at the brewers with cariage. iii.<abbr>s.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>And a kilderkin ſingle Ale or Beere at the Brewers with cariage. xx.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Item a thirindell of the beſt Ale or Beere within and without euery houſe. i.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>And a full quart of good ſingle Ale or Beere within and without euery houſe. ob.</item>
               <item>Item a pound of butter ſweete and new the beſt in the Market. iii.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>And a pound of barrell or ſalt butter in ſhop or in Market. ii.<abbr>d.</abbr> ob.q.</item>
               <item>Item a pound of good Eſſex cheeſe in the ſhop or in Market. i.<abbr>d.</abbr> ob.</item>
               <item>And a pound of good Suffolke cheeſe in ſhop or in Market. i.<abbr>d.</abbr> ob.q.</item>
               <item>Item ſeuen egges the beſt in the Market. ii.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>And three of the ſame egges within euery houſe. i.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Item a ſtone beſt biefe at the butchers weighing viii. pound. xii.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>And a ſtone ſecond biefe at the butchers. xi.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Item a quarter beſt veale at the butchers. ii.<abbr>s.</abbr> ii.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>And a quarter ſecond veale at the butchers. xx.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Item a quarter beſt weather mutton at the butchers. ii.<abbr>s.</abbr> iiii.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>And a quarter ſecond mutton at the butchers. xx.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Item a quarter beſt lambe in the Market. xii.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>And a quarter ſecond lambe in the Market. ix.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Item a fat pigge the beſt in the Market. xiiii.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>And a leane or ſecond pigge in the Market. viii.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Item a couple capons the beſt in the Market. xx.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>And a couple ſecond capons in the Market. xvi.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Item a couple of chickens or rabbets the beſt in the Market. viii.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>And a couple ſecond Chickins or Rabets in the Market. vi.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Item a doſen Pigions the beſt in the Market. xviii.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Item that euery ſouldier or other perſon being placed and appointed in the Bande within the circuite of xx. miles diſtant from her Highneſſe Court, vnder the right honorable the Lord Chamberlaine, her Maieſties Lieutenant of the ſame bande and armie, and receiuing her Maieſties pay by viii.d. the day, hauing to dinner or ſupper good wheaten bread and drinke, beefe, mutton or veale boyled, and pigge, beefe, mutton, veale or lambe roſted, or otherwiſe vpon the fiſh dayes, to haue good wheaten bread and good drinke, ſalte fiſh or ling, egges, butter, peaſe or beanes buttered, and ſo hauing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent and ſufficient thereof for the ſuſtentation of their bodies, euery man to pay for his meale. iii.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Item a pound of Tallowe Candels made of wicke. iii.<abbr>d.</abbr> ob.</item>
               <item>Item a fetherbed for one man one night and ſo depart. i.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Item a fetherbed with neceſſary apparrell thereunto for one man alone by the weeke. vi.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>And the like fetherbed and furniture by the weeke for two lying together. viii.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Item a mattrice or flockbed for one or two together by the weeke. iii.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Item three horſeloaues at the bakers, euery one lofe weyghing xviii. ounces Troie. i.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>And two of the ſame loaues within euery houſe. i.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Item euery C. weight of good ſweete hay weighing Cxii.li. <hi>auoir de poiz</hi> with cariage. viii.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Item euery bottle of hay weighing iiii.li. <hi>auoir de poiz.</hi> ob.</item>
               <item>Item a loade of good ſtrawe for litter with cariage. iiii.<abbr>s.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Item hay and litter day and night for one horſe within euery Inne. iii.<abbr>d.</abbr> ob.</item>
               <item>And the like hay and litter day and night for one horſe within euery other houſe being no Inne. iii.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Item good graſſe for one horſe day and night and ſo depart. ii.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>And the like good graſſe for one horſe alone by the weeke. viii.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Item if any horſe abide in any paſture ouer and aboue one day and one night, then the owner of the ſame horſe to pay for the ſame after the rate of the whole weeke, for ſo long as he ſhall abide in the ſame paſture being as aforeſaid. viii.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Item a loade of talwood keeping the aſſiſe with cariage. iiii.<abbr>s.</abbr> viii.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Item a thouſand billets keeping the aſſiſe with cariage. xi.<abbr>s.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Item a hundred good faggots keeping the aſſiſe with cariage. iiii.<abbr>s.</abbr> iiii.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>And three of the ſame faggots within euery houſe. ii.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Item a quarter of Charcoles conteyning viii. buſhels with cariage. xiiii.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Item a vacant or emptie roome, either chamber roome or ſtable by the whole weeke. iiii.<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Imprinted at London by the deputies of Chriſtopher Barker, Printer to the Queenes moſt excellent Maieſtie. <date>Anno 1588.</date>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum priuilegio Regiae Maieſtatis.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
